Articles of Incorporation

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Pursuant to the provisions of Act 162, Public Acts of 1982 the
undersigned corporation executes the following articles.

ARTICLE 1
        The name of the corporation is: Cyberspace Communications

ARTICLE 2
        The purposes for which the corporation is organized are
set forth, as follows:
        The Corporation is organized for such charitable and
educational purposes as may qualify it for exemption from the
federal income tax under Section 501(c)3 of the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended (or the corresponding
provisions of any future United States internal revenue law.)
More specifically, such purposes include, but are not limited
to, the advancement of public education and scientific
endeavor through interaction with computers, and humans via
computers, using computer conferencing. Further purposes
include the exchange of scientific and technical information
about the various aspects of computer science, such as
operating systems, computer networks, and computer
programming.

ARTICLE 3
        The Corporation is organized on a NONSTOCK basis. The
description and value of its real property assets are: none.
The description and value of its personal property
assets are: none.

        The Corporation is to be finanaced by membership fees,
membership donations, non-member donations and net revenues
from public lectures and events.

        The Corporation is organized on a membership basis.

ARTICLE 4
        The mailing address and registered office for the
Corporation is:
                          4125 Sunset Court
                          Ann Arbor, Mi. 48103

        The name of the registered agent at the office is:

                          Michael Smerza

ARTICLE 5
        The name and address of the incorporator is:
                          Michael Smerza
                          4125 Sunset Court
                          Ann Arbor, Mi. 48103

ARTICLE 6
        The following restrictions will apply to the operations of
the Corporation:

        1. No part of the net earnings of the Corporation shall
inure to the benefit of, or be distributed to its members,
trustees, officers or other private persons, except that the
Corporation shall be authorized and empowered to pay
reasonable compensation for services rendered and to make
payments and distributions in furtherance of the purposes set
forth in Article II.

        2. No substantial part of the activities of the
Corporation shall be the carrying on of progaganda, or
otherwise attempting to influence legislation, and the
Corporation shall not participate in, or intervene in
(including the publishing or distribution of statements) any
political campaign on behalf of any candidate for public
office.

        3. Notwithstanding any other provision of these articles,
the Corporation shall not carry on any other activities not
permitted to be carried on (a) by a corporation exempt from
federal income tax under section 501(c)3 of the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986 (or the corresponding provision of any
future United States internal revenue law) or (b) by a
corporation, contributions to which are deductible under
section 170 (c)(2) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (or
the corresponding provision of any future United States
internal revenue law).

        4. In the event of the dissolution of the Corporation, all
of the Corporations's assets, real and personal, shall be
distributed to such charitable organization or organizations
as are qualified as tax-exempt under Section 501(c)(3) of the
Code or corresponding provisions of any subsequent Federal
income tax laws, as the Board of trustees of the Corporation
shall determine. Any such assets not so disposed of, for
whatever reason, shall be disposed of by the order of the
Circuit Court for the County of Washtenaw to such organization
or organizations, as said Court shall determine, which are
organized and operated exlusively for charitable purposes.

        5. In the event the Corporation is determined to be a
"private foundation" as that term is defined in Code Section
509(a), then for the purpose of complying with the
requirements of code Section 508(e), for all taxable years
commencing on or after the date of incorporation, the
Corporation shall:

                A. Distribute its income and such part of its capital
                as may be required by law for each taxable year at
                such time and in such manner as not to become subject
                to the tax on undistributed income imposed by Code
                Section 4942, or corresponding provisions of any
                subsequent Federal tax laws;

                B. Not engage in any act of self-dealing as defined
                in Code Section 4941, or corresponding provisions of
                any subsequent Federal tax laws;

                C. Not retain any excess business holdings as defined
                in Code Section 4943, or corresponding provisions of
                any subsequent Federal tax laws;

                D. Not make any investments in such manner as to
                subject it to tax under Code Section 4944, or
                corresponding provisons of any subsequent Federal
                tax laws;

                E. Not make any taxable expenditures as defined
                in Code Section 4945, or corresponding provisions
                of any subsequent Federal tax laws.

ARTICLE 7
        Except as otherwise provided by law, a volunteer director
of the Corporation is not personally liable to the Corporation
or its members for monetary damages for a breach of the
officer's fiduciary duty.

        The Corporation assumes all liability to any person other
than the Corporation or its members for all acts or omissions
of a volunteer director incurred in good faith performance of
their duty as an officer occurring on or after the date of
incorporation.

ARTICLE 8
        The bylaws of Cyberspace Communications are the final
authority in matters of conflict between documents
except when a provision of proposal to change a provision in
the bylaws would countermand the legal restrictions of a
nonprofit tax exempt corporation. For such a provision or
change in a provision to be the final authority, the
membership must specifically vote to adopt or revoke the
provision in question at a meeting as specified in the bylaws.

                                  Signed______________________
                                          (Michael E. Smerza)

                                  Date____May 15, 1991________

$Id: articles.xhtml 1438 2014-03-23 16:39:04Z kentn $

Bylaws of Cyberspace Communications Inc. (Grex)

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

        +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++

               Cyberspace Communications / Grex Bylaws

      PREAMBLE
 
  It is the objective of this organization to provided an
  open-access computer conferencing system for the education,
  intellectual enrichment, and entertainment of its users through
  the peaceable interchange of information and ideas.  To this end,
  we establish these bylaws for the governance of the
  organization.
 
 
      ARTICLE 1:  NAME
 
  This organization shall be known as "Cyberspace Communications".
  The computer conferencing system provided by the organization is
  known as "Grex".
 
 
      ARTICLE 2:  MEMBERSHIP

  a.  Any individual or institution supporting the goals and objectives of
      this organization as enumerated in the Preamble, and who agrees to
      abide by these bylaws and pay dues, is eligible for membership.
 
  b.  To be eligible to vote, an individual must be a current member and
      have paid a minimum of three months dues.

  c.  Institutional members are never eligible to vote.
 
 
      ARTICLE 3:  BOARD OF DIRECTORS

  a.  The Board of Directors (BOD) shall consist of five individual members of
      Grex, and shall include a chairperson, a secretary, and a treasurer.
 
  b.  The BOD shall maintain an awareness of and discuss issues
      relevant to Grex's status and (excepting issues whose
      discussion might compromise system security) shall keep the
      users informed of these issues.
 
  c.  The BOD shall make decisions related to system maintenance,
      staff responsibilities and appointments, and issues related
      to daily business.

  d.  The BOD shall hold face-to-face meetings on a regular, bimonthly basis,
      and in addition may hold special meetings if necessary.  A quorum  
      consists of three BOD members.  A board member will be considered in 
      attendance at a meeting if he or she can communicate with and be 
      understood by all the other attendees.
  

  e.  The time, place, and agenda of each BOD meeting shall be
      publicized one week in advance of the meeting, or as soon
      thereafter as feasible.  Meetings shall normally be open to
      all users of Grex, except that portions of meetings dealing
      with sensitive system security or personnel issues may be
      held in closed executive session.
 
  f.  The chairperson is responsible for calling BOD meetings and
      organizing the agenda.  For the purposes of incorporation
      papers, the chairperson shall also be known as the
      president.
 
  g.  The secretary shall take minutes at all BOD meetings and
      make them available to the users of Grex in a timely fashion,
      shall maintain an up-to-date list of all officers, members,
      and staff, and shall handle routine correspondence.
 
  h.  The treasurer shall collect all dues and other monies and
      deposit them in the organization's checking account, shall
      pay all bills by check, shall keep records of all trans-
      actions, and shall publicly post a monthly financial report.
 
  i.  The BOD may establish committees as they deem necessary.
 
 
      ARTICLE 4:  ELECTIONS AND TERMS OF OFFICE
 
  a.  BOD members shall be elected to two-year terms, that begin
      on January 1 of each year.  Terms of office shall be
      staggered, with 4 board positions being filled beginning in
      even-numbered years and 3 in odd-numbered years.
 
  b.  If an office is vacated before expiration of its term, an
      election to fill the vacancy shall take place within three
      months.

  c.  Nominations for the BOD will be submitted by November 15th.
      Any person may submit nominations.  All nominees must be 
      individual Grex members as of the start of the voting period.
      Board elections will be held between the 1st and 15th of December.
      The required number of candidates receiving the largest number of
      votes are seated on the board commencing January 1st.

  d.  A BOD member shall be removed from office if they resign,
      not be available for meetings or respond to BOD
      communications for a period of four months, or be voted out
      of office by a vote of the membership, with 3/4 of the
      ballots cast in favor of removal.

  
      ARTICLE 5:  VOTING PROCEDURES
 
  a.  Any member of Grex may make a motion by entering it as the
      text of a discussion item in a computer conference on Grex
      designated for this purpose.  The item is then used for
      discussion of the motion.  All Grex users may participate in
      the discussion.  No action on the motion is taken for two
      weeks.
 
  b.  In order for the motion to be voted on, at least 10% of the
      eligible voting membership must endorse bringing the proposal
      to a vote.  Endorsement shall consist of a statement by the
      member in the discussion item agreeing that the motion should
      be voted on.  A member may withdraw his or her endorsement at
      any time prior to the close of the endorsement period as
      defined in section (c) below.
 
  c.  When at least two weeks have passed, the author may post a
      final wording of the motion and request that it be voted on.
      Following posting of the final wording, members shall have
      forty-eight hours to add an endorsement or withdraw a previous
      endorsement.  At the end of this period, if the motion has the
      necessary number of endorsements, it shall be voted on.  The
      vote is begun as soon as feasible and is conducted online over
      a period of ten days.  If within thirty days from the date that
      the item was posted the author does not request a vote or the
      necessary number of endorsements have not been obtained, the
      motion is considered to have lapsed and is not eligible for
      voting.
 
  d.  Simultaneous voting on two or more motions is permissible,
      subject to limitations of the voting software.  However,
      two motions may not be voted on simultaneously if one
      is contradictory to or implies a modification of effect
      to the other.  In such a case, the motion posted first shall
      take precedence in voting order.
 
  e.  A motion will be considered to have passed if more
      votes were cast in favor than against, except as provided
      for bylaw amendments.
 
  f.  For voting purposes, a day will run midnight to midnight, local
      Grex time.  In the event of continuous system downtime of 24
      hours or more, the voting period will be adjusted to compensate.
 
 
      ARTICLE 6:  DUES
 
  a.  Membership dues are $18 per year, or $2 per month.

  b.  The fiscal year shall begin on January 1 of each year.  The
      incumbent treasurer shall close the books prior to this date.
 
  c.  The BOD shall be responsible for keeping the membership
      informed as to Grex's financial status.  Should circumstances
      warrant a change in membership dues, the membership will be
      notified and the issue discussed and put to a vote according
      to the procedures of AThe BOD shall hold face-to-face meetings on 
      a regular, bimonthly basis, and in addition may hold special meetings if
      necessary.  A quorum consists of three BOD members.  A board member will
      be considered in attendance at a meeting if he or she can communicate with
      and be understood by all the other attendees.
 
   d. Dues paid to cover a membership of two years or less will
      not be affected by an increase in dues.
 
 
      ARTICLE 7:  AMENDMENTS TO THE BYLAWS

  Amendments to these bylaws may be proposed and voted upon at any
  time according to the procedures of Article 5a. In order for a
  proposed amendment to take effect, a 3/4 majority voting in favor
  of the change is required.
 
  
      ARTICLE 8:  DISSOLVEMENT
 
  In the event the membership is unable to support Cyberspace
  Communications, all property belonging to the club shall be
  sold.  The remaining cash assets, after paying final bills, shall
  be donated to a charitable organization, as determined by the
  BOD.  All elected officers shall then be released from their
  obligations and the corporation dissolved.
 
 
      ADDENDUM
 
  It is understood that it may not be feasible to hold the first
  election for the Board of Directors by the dates specified in
  Article 5.  An election for the initial Board of Directors shall
  be held within 90 days of the adoption of these bylaws.  All
  seven BOD positions will be filled in this election, with the
  four candidates receiving the most votes having two-year terms
  and the next three candidates one-year terms.
 
        +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++


History of Amendments:  

January 12, 1995:  Articles 4d, 4e, 5b, and 7  (eliminating quorum
                   criteria)

February 1, 1997:  Article 4d (membership status re: Board of
                   Director candidacy and nominators)

July 20, 1997:     Articles 2a, 2b, 2c, 3a, and 4d (membership
                   status for organizations)

Sept. 29, 2002:    Article 3d  (board member attendance at
                   BOD meetings)

March 24, 2004:    Article 5 (membership endorsement required
                   prior to a vote)

October 31, 2010:  Article 3a, 3d (board size and quorum)

October 31, 2010:  Article 6a (change in dues)

March 22, 2013:    Article 4b, 4c (eliminate term limits for board members)
  

$Id: bylaws.xhtml 1438 2014-03-23 16:39:04Z kentn $

Wizard in Training

Your GREX Beginner's Handbook

Table of Contents

Janitorial Staff
A Bit of History
How GREX Works
Making Sense of This (Web) Booklet

Type Conventions
A Note about !s

The Psychology of Electronic Communication

Emoticons

Netiquette: Social Lubricant in Cyberspace

Flames
Advertising

GREX Membership: What and Why
Donations: The Lifeblood of a Bottom Feeder

Donations Especially Useful to GREX

The Ecology of a Small System

Mail Limits
Resources: The Final Frontier
Why GREX Isnt an Internet Service Provider (ISP)

Off to a Good Start - Getting Connected to GREX

Dialing in to GREX
Using Telnet to Connect to GREX
Logging in

Creating a New Account

Finding Your Terminal Type

Selecting a Shell
Changing Things about your Login
Getting More Help

The Info Conference
GREX On-Line Helpers
The Trouble Login
More Documentation

Wandering through the Conferences: the Real GREX!

Terminology

|

Getting into the Conferencing System
Using the Conferencing System

Prompts
Selecting a Conference
Reading a Conference
Seeing a List of Items
Reading Specific Items
Reading New Items in a Conference
Responding to an Interesting Item
Viewing Particular Responses
Entering a New Item
Forgetting a Boring or Annoying Item

Getting The Hang Of E-Mail

Selecting a Mailer

Party

Noises

The World Wide Web

Accessing the Web through Lynx
Making Your Own Home Page on GREX

Peek into Your Mathom Closet
Finger
Going One-on-One: Using Chat, Write, Talk, and Tel

Chat and Write
Talk
Tel
Preventing People from Writing to You

Text Files and Editors

Your Home Directory
Editors
Using an Editor from within PicoSpan or Mail

Uploading and Downloading Files

Transferring Files over a Dial-up Connection
FTP

UNIX (Whats That?)
Bibliography
The GREX Statement of Principles

Table of Contents

Janitorial Staff

The 2002 Cyberspace Communications Board of Directors:
        Eric Bassey (other) - Chair
        Anne Perry (mooncat) - Secretary
        Mark Conger (aruba) - Treasurer
        Mary Remmers (mary)
        STeve André' (steve)
        Greg Fleming (flem)
        Marcus Watts (mdw)
                E-mail the board at board@grex.org

The Grex Staff:
        STeve André' (steve)              Charles Mitchell (arthurp)
        Mic Giansiracusa (spooked)      John Remmers (remmers)
        Steve Gibbard (scg)             Marcus Watts (mdw)
        Dan Gryniewicz (dang)           Jan Wolter (janc)
        Scott Helmke (scott)            Steve Weiss (srw)
        Valerie Mates (valerie)
                E-mail the staff at staff@grex.org

Conference Administrators (cfadms):
        Walter Cramer  (i)              Valerie Mates (valerie)
        Scott Helmke (scott)            John Remmers (remmers)

Webmaster:
        Steve Weiss (srw)

Software Designers:
        Valerie Mates (valerie)         Mathom
        Mic Giansiracusa (spooked)      New Menus
        John Remmers (remmers)          Vote, Web Vote
        Marcus Watts (mdw)              PicoSpan, Newuser, Telnet Queue, Spam blocks, a bunch of other stuff
        Steve Weiss (srw)               Lynx Menu, Backtalk
        Jan Wolter (janc)               Party, Write, Mesg, Gate, Backtalk, Web Newuser

This handbook written by:
        Misti Tucker (mta)              Mark Conger (aruba)
With help from:
        STeve André (steve)              Valerie Mates (valerie)
adapted for the Web by:
        Eric Bassey (other)

Table of Contents

A Bit of History

Grex was conceived in 1990 by a dozen people with little more in common than a love for computer conferencing. Over the course of several months, they met once a week to discuss their ideas about how the ideal system might be run, and to work out a common vision. The process wasn't always smooth; each founder had very clear ideas and there were sometimes differences that were very hard to resolve. They persevered and finally arrived at a consensus.

Once their vision for Grex was formed, they spent the next several months working to pull the system together. Once they had collected the money and equipment their new system would need just to open to the public, they agreed amongst themselves that they would finance the system's operations out of their own pockets for the first year.

On July 18, 1991, Grex opened its lines to the modeming public.

Grex got its start running on a donated Sun-2/170, with only 5 phone lines, 4 Meg of RAM, and 2 ancient 80 Meg Fujitsu SMD hard drives. It was housed in the warehouse of a generous local business owner, Ken Ascher, for just the cost of the electricity and telephones. NetMeg, owned and operated by Meg Geddes, supplied the Internet mail feed.

Things have changed some since then. Grex is now living in its own apartment, a 12' by 12' room in a building near downtown Ann Arbor. We're running on a Sun-4/670 with 384MB of RAM, 31 gigabytes of disk and 7 dial-in phone lines. Most important, Grex is now attached to the Internet by a dedicated DSL connection!

Table of Contents

How GREX Works

Cyberspace Communications, Inc., is a Michigan non-profit corporation.

Any user may become a member of Grex just by making a donation of $2 a month or $18 a year to the system. The membership makes all major decisions about the system's direction.

The Board of Directors, elected by the members of Grex, makes routine administrative decisions. The Board normally meets once a month. Members (and anyone else who's interested) are welcome to attend.

Daily operations of Grex are managed by an all volunteer staff, which is responsible for keeping Grex up and running smoothly. The staff is appointed by the board and is responsible for keeping Grex up and happy. It's a thankless job that keeps them busy for hours every week. (Thanks, folks!) Normally, the staff is represented at all board meetings.

Table of Contents

Making Sense of This (Web) Booklet

There are a few things you'll need to understand to make sense of the instructions in this (web) booklet.

Type Conventions

If I want you to type something,

it will look like this.

If I want to show you what the words on the screen will be,

it will look like this.

So if you see:

Ok: chat

it means, type the word chat where you see Ok: on the screen.

A Note about !s

There is a convention that many UNIX programs observe: when you want to run one program from within another, you type a ! (pronounced bang) before the command. Most of the examples shown in this booklet dont use a ! , but in some cases (such as when you are at a menu prompt) you may need one. So in general, if a command doesnt work right for you, try putting a ! in front of it.

Table of Contents

The Psychology of Electronic Communication

Communicating electronically is different from talking face to face or over the telephone. Without the feedback of facial and vocal cues, it's easy to misunderstand, especially because English is an inherently ambiguous language.

Take the time to wordsmith your comments. When you remove the ambiguity, you ensure that the hundreds of people who will read your words will understand them as you meant them. That can make all the difference in the world, especially since Grex has users coming in from all over the world, many of whom speak English as a second or third language.

It's also a good idea to give other people the benefit of the doubt if they say something that can be taken more than one way. As you become more familiar to the Grex old-timers and more familiar with the verbal shorthand we've developed, you'll find it becomes second nature.

Emoticons

One way to help keep your responses from being misinterpreted is to use emoticons (sometimes called smileys) to help readers know what facial expression to associate with your words. For instance, if you say something in jest, it's a good idea to put a :) after it. If you're sad about something, use :( . If you want to wink at someone, use ;) . There are many other possibilities - don't hesitate to experiment.

Table of Contents

Netiquette: Social Lubricant in Cyberspace

As with every community, Cyberspace has a system of norms that allows us to get along in harmony most of the time. Various nooks have variations on the norms, of course. An excellent Internet convention is to try to be generous in interpreting what you read, but diplomatic and refined in what you say.

Flames

A flame is a personal attack on another user, usually in a public forum like the conferences or Party. Public flame fests are unpleasant and make the system a stressful place to hang out.

From time to time it's likely that someone will make a remark that makes you really angry. When that happens, remember:

Take time to cool off before you respond.
If the remark was intentionally provocative, the best response is no response.
Respond to the idea and not the speaker.
If you feel you absolutely must make a personal remark, please take it to e-mail and keep it private.

Advertising

Grex is a not-for-profit organization. It is not a platform for serious business transactions. (This applies to private individuals as well as companies.) We do however have a classifieds conference specifically set up to let people with something to peddle meet people who want to barter or buy.

Table of Contents

GREX Membership: What and Why

Becoming a member of Grex is easy. You can type

support

or sometimes

!support

at almost any prompt to get more information.

But what is a Grex membership, and why should you bother? After all, Grex is a free system.

Well, yes, you are free to use Grex, whether you're a member or not. But when you make a donation and become a Grex member, you buy a little piece of our collective. You become a part owner in an exciting social experiment. You get a voice in the running of the system, and most important, you help ensure that this valuable community resource can continue to be available to everyone.

Grex is entirely supported by its users. No large corporations or government agencies contribute any of the money needed to keep the system running. This means Grex is really and truly a grass roots organization, and it has the freedom to change in whatever directions its members would like. But it also means that it is entirely dependent on the good will of its users. If enough people don't commit to supporting Grex, it may go away.

Table of Contents

Donations: The Lifeblood of a Bottom Feeder

Without donations, Grex wouldn't exist today. We are always happy to accept any computer equipment in danger of becoming boat anchors and door stops. We use what we can to expand Grex. We repair and sell the rest to electronics hobbyists to buy the things we need. If you have out of date equipment around the house, please feel free to let us know! If you know of something that is in danger of being pushed off a dock, please give us a call! Contact us by sending e-mail to staff@grex.org.

Donations Especially Useful to GREX

If you have old Sun equipment that you don't need, we'd love to hear about it. We're also always interested in things like PCs and Macs, SCSI disks, RAM chips, modems, commercial software, and printers.

Table of Contents

The Ecology of a Small System

Mail Limits

Because of our limited resources, we ask that you limit the amount of mail passing through your account (both incoming and outgoing) to 100K per day or less. Please also refrain from sending large files. If you have to send them, please break them into 100K chunks first and send those out, one per day. Also, please don't sign up for a mailing list unless you're sure you can keep up with the traffic and not let the mail accumulate in your inbox!

Resources: The Final Frontier

Grex is an all volunteer system, supported, maintained, and expanded with funds donated by members and friends. As with any group that relies on the beneficence of the public, sometimes we can't grow fast enough to keep up with demand. It's important to realize that we all share Grex's resources equally. When the resources run out, we also share equally in the hassles and the responsibilities to help solve the problem. Please don't keep large files in your home directory for more than a few days and please read and remove your mail regularly.

Why GREX Is not an Internet Service Provider (ISP)

Our Internet link is currently one DSL line. This means that Grex isnt all that fast compared to the big guys that are well connected. While we're very grateful for the connection, the size of the link does require some restraint on everyone's part to avoid overtaxing it. Since lots of things use this link, like telnet, FTP, e-mail, etc., you shouldnt think of Grex as an Internet provider. Think of us instead as a conferencing system that has some Internet capabilities.

Table of Contents

Off to a Good Start - Getting Connected to GREX

There are two ways to log into Grex: by dialing into Grex's modem bank and by telnetting in over the Internet.

Dialing in to GREX

Dialing in to Grex requires comparatively little equipment.
You need:

a computer or terminal
a modem
working telephone service
a communication package such as ProComm, Telix, Kermit, or the Windows Terminal program.

Of course, it can't hurt to have some documentation about using Grex, or a friend who's familiar with the system, too.

Setting Up Your Communication Parameters
Almost any terminal program, on any computer, can connect to Grex. Refer to your documentation for the details of how your modem and communication program work.

Next set your modem to the highest speed it will support, up to 14400 bps.

Dialing
When you've set your communication parameters, you're ready to dial Grex. Tell your terminal program to dial

(734) 761-3000

When your modem connects to Grex, you'll hear a whistling in several tones. When it finishes, you'll see a welcome message on the screen, followed by the prompt

login:

Using Telnet to Connect to GREX

If your computer is already connected to the Internet through some other service, you can access Grex with a telnet program. Most of the time that means typing the command

telnet grex.org

Or it might mean starting the telnet program and then telling it to open a connection to grex.org. If you connected correctly, you should see the same prompt as above:

Logging in

*Note: If this is your first time on Grex, see Creating a New Account.

Type your Grex login ID (the one selected when you ran the Newuser program) at the login prompt. For instance, if your login is waffles, type

login: waffles

Next you'll be prompted for your password. If your password is pancakes, type

waffles's Password: pancakes

Grex won't show the letters you type here so that no one can learn your password by watching over your shoulder as you log in.

Finally, Grex will show you the terminal type youve selected. If you're logging in from the same type of computer as usual, just press the enter key; otherwise type in the appropriate terminal type.

*Note: If you always log in from the same type of terminal, you can use the change program to tell Grex not to prompt you every time. See Changing Things About Your Login.

Table of Contents

Creating a New Account

Creating an account on Grex is free. You don't have to send money or identification, you can create a new account and start conferencing during the same session!

To create a new account, simply type

login: newuser

The Grex Newuser program will tell you something about the system, then will ask you a series of questions. This booklet contains the information you'll need to answer the hard questions.

In answering the personal questions, keep in mind that 1) creating a new account doesnt obligate you to anything, ever and 2) you'll decide whether to let everyone see the information you entered. If you put the privacy switch on, only staff will see your information. (Staff won't divulge your private information without a court order.)

But, of course, if you don't want to answer any personal questions, that's OK too. We do recommend, however, that you give some contact information to Newuser, such as an alternate e-mail address or a physical address. That way, if you ever forget your password, you can send the Grex staff mail from your other address, and they will reset the password for you.

Finding Your Terminal Type

The computer and communications software you use to access Grex are together called your terminal. UNIX systems can theoretically be accessed by many users using very different computers and communication software. For this reason Grex and systems like it support a wide variety of terminal types. This, as you might expect, causes some confusion.

There are some programs on Grex that need to know how to talk to your terminal, which means you can't use them if you don't know your terminal type. That makes it worth figuring it out what terminal type you are using.

*Note: You don't have to know your terminal type to use Grex, but Grex will work better for you if you do.

Usually the terminal type is explained in the communication program documentation under Terminal Emulation. Fortunately, almost all communication programs these days have the ability to look like a vt100 terminal (that's the name of a terminal standard developed by Digital Corporation), so if you aren't sure try that. If you find out that you made the wrong choice in the Newuser program, don't worry. You can change it later. (Computers are wonderful that way!)

Table of Contents

Selecting a Shell

A shell is a UNIX program which gets run as soon as you log in, and keeps running until you log off. All other programs that you run are launched from within your shell. It's kind of like a stage on which everything happens.

Grex offers a number of different shells for you to choose from. Which one you should choose depends on how familiar you are with UNIX and how you want to use Grex.

The Menu Shell

The menu shell is very popular because it lets you choose most of Grex's options from a simple menu. It doesn't explain what those options mean, but if you've had some experience with conferencing systems this is your best bet.

The Lynx Shell

The Lynx shell gives you the most information and takes the guess work out of using Grex. If you're completely unfamiliar with conferencing systems, UNIX, and the Internet, this is probably your best bet. It does take a certain amount of patience, though, because there is a lot of information and it continues to show up whether you need it or not.

The BBS Shell

If you're familiar with conferencing systems and you know generally what you want to do here on Grex, whether it's conferencing, e-mail, chatting, or something else, you may find the BBS shell the easiest way to go. It requires that you learn a few simple commands, but it's fast and flexible. For a BBS Tipsheet, send a SASE to Grex INFO at the address listed in the Getting More Help section .

Programmer Shells

(csh, zsh, ksh, sh, tcsh, and bash)
If you're familiar with UNIX and command-line interfaces and you want the full power of a UNIX system available to you when you're using Grex, you may find the C shell (csh), or one of the other UNIX shells mentioned above, the most efficient way to go. They require that you know standard UNIX commands, but they are quick and flexible. For a C shell Tipsheet, send a SASE to Grex INFO at the address listed in the Getting More Help section.

Table of Contents

Changing Things about your Login

When you run the Grex Newuser program, you make a number of decisions about things like what character would be used for backspace, which editor to use, etc.

If you've decided that something isn't quite right for you and you'd like to change it, the change program will help you fix things. From inside PicoSpan, type:

!change

or, from another shell, type:

change

The change program is completely menu driven and will prompt you each step of the way. It does all the hard stuff for you.

Table of Contents

Getting More Help

There are a number of good ways to get answers to your Grexish questions or problems. The first thing you might try is typing

help

(or possibly

!help

) wherever you happen to be. If that doesn't tell you what you need to know, try one of these other options.

The Info Conference

One of the best ways to get answers is to join the info conference, where people have been asking and answering questions throughout Grex's existence. If you don't find the answer to your question there, you can always post it and check back in a couple of hours.

GREX On-Line Helpers

If you have an urgent question, you can type:

write help

That notifies a Grex helper (if one is logged on) that you have a question. Please wait several minutes for a response, since the helper may be helping someone else or in the middle of an uninterruptible process when you call.

A Grex helper is just a more experienced user who has agreed to answer basic Grex questions. Not every helper will know the answer to every question, and helpers don't have any capabilities (other than knowledge) that you don't have.

The Trouble Login

If you have trouble logging in, you can log in as trouble. That login automatically sends mail to the people who can help you straighten out account problems. Be sure to give us the information about your account and how we can reach you. (Staff clairvoyance is a very limited resource.)

More Documentation

If there's a document you want, or you need more information about a specific topic, send a request to
comments@grex.org or mail your request to:
Cyberspace Communications
P.O. Box 4432
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48106

Table of Contents

Wandering through the Conferences: the Real GREX!

While it's true that Grex has many services to offer, conferencing is the heart of the system. Without our conferences, we'd be little more than another file stop on the information highway. You'll find more than 100 conferences on Grex, with topics ranging from hobbies to public issues, from computers and games to life roles, with new conferences starting frequently.

So, what is computer conferencing? It's a way of letting a group of people talk to each other over time, with the computer acting as a scribe, keeping track of all that has been said. At any point, any participant in a conference can go back and see everything that has been discussed since the last restart.

Terminology

A conference is a general area for discussion of related topics. (You may have heard the term forum used elsewhere to describe what we call a conference on Grex.) For example the kitchen conference is where people talk about food, cooking and restaurants. In the micros conference the topic is microcomputers. The coop conference is where you can learn more about how Grex is run and participate in the decision making process. And the smalls conference is dedicated to conversation about living with and raising children.

Each conference consists of items, which anyone in the conference can enter. An item is a topic for conversation related to the conference subject. For instance, in the smalls conference you might find items about toilet training, schools, and cute remarks the little shavers make. You might think of an item as a comment you've written on a piece of paper, and stuck on a bulletin board or kiosk in a busy place. As people wander by, they can read your item. After reading it, they can add a comment or response to the bottom of the page.

Over time, an item might have many responses and new conversations (called drift) may evolve from the original item; some popular items have hundreds of responses. Interaction between the participants of the conference spurs further discussion and brings up new points, which may spin off into new items...or not.

So, to summarize the terminology: A conference is a place where people discuss a particular topic, such as cooking or children. Each conference consists of items, each of which is a discussion. Items may have any number of responses, entered by any number of people.

Table of Contents

Getting into the Conferencing System

Grex's conferences can now be accessed in two different ways: through PicoSpan and through Backtalk. PicoSpan is a program written by Grex founder Marcus Watts in 1984, and it's the easiest thing to use when you're already logged on to Grex. Backtalk was written by Grex staffers Jan Wolter and Steve Weiss in 1996-98, and it operates through the World Wide Web. If you have access to the web, you can check out Backtalk by going to www.grex.org and following a few links.

Since this handbook is mainly about what you do when you're logged in to Grex, it will focus on PicoSpan. First, getting into it:

If You Use the Menu Shell:
Select

B

for BBS.
If You Use the Lynx Shell:
From the initial screen, choose

Grex Activities Menu

followed by

Computer conferencing

.
If You Use the BBS Shell:
If you selected the BBS shell when you created your account, you should see the

Ok:

prompt as soon as you log in to Grex. That means you're already in PicoSpan.
If You Use One of the Programmer Shells:
To get into the PicoSpan conferencing system from another shell, type:

bbs

at your shell's prompt.

Table of Contents

Using the Conferencing System

Prompts

First things first. The two basic prompts that PicoSpan gives you are:

Ok:

which means that you are reading a conference but not a specific item, and

Respond or pass?

which you see after you have just read an item.

*Note: Your prompts may differ slightly from the above. For instance, they may include a few lines of explanatory text or mention more possible actions. Dont let that throw you - all the examples in this handbook still apply.

Selecting a Conference

When you begin conferencing for the first time, you will automatically start out in the agora conference. Agora is the main meeting hall on Grex, through which virtually everyone passes at one time or another. Almost any subject might come up in here so you'll probably find something there that interests you.

Many people never go any farther than agora, but there are lots of other choices! To see an updated list of all the conferences, type:

Ok: help conf

You'll be presented with a list of conferences sorted by subject. If you'd like to look in on, say, the kitchen conference, type:

Ok: join kitchen

The first time you do that you'll get a message saying

You are not a member of /bbs/kitchen2. Do you wish to Join, quit, or help?

Type J to join the conference.

Reading a Conference

Once you've found a conference you're interested in, you really only need to know a few commands to get started using PicoSpan. The commands are browse, read, and respond.

Seeing a List of Items

The browse command presents a list of all the items in the conference. It will display the item name and the number that identifies that item to the system.

Once you enter a conference, type:

Ok: browse

A list of the items available will scroll across your screen. Note the numbers of any items that interest you.

*Note: Many PicoSpan commands can be abbreviated. For instance, browse can be abbreviated as b . We won't discuss all the abbreviations here, but you may want to guess at them to save yourself some keystrokes.

If you've been in a conference before and want to see which items have changed since your last visit, type:

Ok: browse new

Reading Specific Items

Once you've found an item that interests you, the read command shows you the text of a particular item. If you don't specify an item number, PicoSpan will show all the items that you haven't read yet. (Not a good idea until you've gotten familiar with a conference.)

To read, say, item 5, type:

Ok: read 5

If you want to read several items, you can list all of them separated by a single space and they will come up in the order you listed them. So to read items 1, 7 and 4 in that order, type:

Ok: read 1 7 4

Reading New Items in a Conference

Once you've been reading a conference for a while, you might want to read everything anyone has said there since you last checked in.

To read all the new responses in a conference, type:

Ok: read new

To read all new responses in items 1, 7, and 4, type:

Ok: read 1 7 4 new

Responding to an Interesting Item

When you've finished reading an item, you may decide that you want to make a comment about the subject under discussion.

PicoSpan will automatically ask if you want to respond or pass. To respond to the item, enter:

Respond or pass? r

Then type in the text of your response. When you're done, type Ctrl-D or place a period on a line by itself and hit enter.

To pass on to the next item without responding, enter:

Respond or pass? p

(Actually, if you just hit the enter key without typing a command, thats the same as typing p.) If you are interested in responding to an item, but would rather do it later, you can type:

Respond or pass? postpone

The item will show up again the next time you read new responses.

Viewing Particular Responses

Responses, like items, all have numbers. Because a single item can have hundreds of responses, you may want to go back and view a few of them at a time without rereading the whole item. To view, say, response number 50, type:

Respond or pass? only 50

To view all the responses since response 34, simply type:

Respond or pass? 34

To view the original text of the item, type:

Respond or pass? only 0

To see the title of the item, type:

Respond or pass? header

Entering a New Item

Once you've been around a while, you'll very likely want to start a new item of your own to discuss something that no one has brought up yet.

To enter a brand new item:

Ok: enter

PicoSpan will then ask you for the text of the item and its title.

Forgetting a Boring or Annoying Item

The forget command lets you tell PicoSpan that you don't want to follow an individual item. When the topic of an item doesn't interest you or you find something irritating about the drift of the conversation, you can easily dismiss the item from the list of those you'll read in the future. (So the next time you do a read new or a browse, it won't show up even if it has new responses.)

To forget an item you have just read, type:

Respond or pass? forget

Table of Contents

Getting The Hang Of E-Mail

Using e-mail, you can: get to know people around the world, get back in touch with friends and family you haven't seen in far too long, and keep up to date on plans with your local friends.

E-mail here on Grex won't cost you anything, so feel free to send and receive lots of messages -- only, please, keep them reasonably small. We do have a limited amount of bandwidth to serve the more than 3000 users who log in each day.

So, how do you get started using e-mail? The first step is to collect some e-mail addresses for people you want to send mail to, and to give your e-mail address to people you want to hear from.

Your e-mail address here is yourloginid@grex.org. In other words, if your login on Grex is tina, your address is: tina@grex.org

Selecting a Mailer

Grex offers several programs to allow you to send and receive mail. The only difference is in the way you use the program to read and send messages. Grex transmits all e-mail the same way, so that it will be compatible with other systems on the Internet.

Pine

Pine is a simple, menu driven mailer. Many people who are used to using a mouse prefer this mailer. (Its main drawback is that it can be quite slow when Grex is busy.) You need to have your terminal type set correctly to use Pine. To run Pine, type:

Ok: pine

Elm

Elm is also a simple, menu driven mailer. It's similar in concept to Pine, but it's been around longer and the details of how it works are a bit different. Elm, like Pine, requires that your terminal type be set correctly. To run Elm, type:

Ok: elm

UNIX Mail

The UNIX Mail mailer will work on any terminal. It's a command line mailer, so it's a bit trickier to get used to, but once you get the hang of it, it's also faster to use and less of a strain on Grex's resources than the other two. To run Mail, type:

Ok: !mail

Table of Contents

Party

Party is a very popular program on Grex which allows users to have conversations in real time. It's similar to what are called chat rooms on the Internet.

You enter Party by typing:

Ok: party

If other people are already there (as is almost always the case), very soon you will start to see messages from them appearing on your screen. You can respond by simply typing what you want to say. Hit the Enter key to send the text to everyone.

Noises

Occasionally you may see text appear on your screen which looks like:

<robh hugs steve>

That is called a noise. Party has a table of many noises you can make. You make a noise by typing the noise's name followed by any parameters it takes. To make the noise above, for instance, robh typed:

/hug steve

To see a table of all the noises you can make, just enter a slash (/) by itself. But be warned, the list is over a thousand lines long. There is a catch all noise called emote which you may want to know about, because it lets you use it however you want. For instance, if robh types:

/emote quacks like a duck

everyone will see:

<robh quacks like a duck>

Table of Contents

The World Wide Web

The popularity of the World Wide Web is what has driven the Internet boom of the 1990s. That boom promises to become one of the most significant changes in our society begun in the twentieth century.

Accessing the Web through Lynx

Grex provides access to the textual portions of the Web through a browser called Lynx. We would like to be able to show you pictures too, but our link just can't handle that much traffic.

To run Lynx, type:

Ok: !lynx

You will see a web page on Grex which will help you to get started. There is lots of help for Lynx available online, but here are a few tips:

If you know the address of a web page you want to visit, type g followed by the address.
The up and down arrow keys are used for moving the cursor around within a page. Use them to highlight a link you want to follow and press Enter to go there.
The left and right arrow keys move you backward and forward within the list of pages you have visited.
Hit ? for help.
If your screen gets messed up for some reason, you can have Lynx redraw it by hitting Ctrl-R.
Hit q to quit out of Lynx.

Making Your Own Home Page on GREX

If you'd like to create your own little corner of the Web you can do it on Grex. Its not quite as simple as typing in a text document; you will need to know HTML (Hypertext Markup Language). Many references are available both on the Web and in bookstores on HTML. And of course, you can't store pictures or multimedia files on Grex, but your page can contain references to them if they are elsewhere.

To make your own homepage on Grex, type:

Ok: !mkhomepage

You'll get a menu which lets you choose to create a new homepage or edit an old one, and also gives you more information. If you create a new one, it will be a file called index.html in a subdirectory of your home directory called www. The address people use to access your page depends on your user ID; for instance, if you login as janc, then your home page is: http://www.grex.org/~janc

If you'd like to see the list of frequently asked questions about Grex web pages, there is a link to it on the first page you see when you run Lynx.

Table of Contents

Peek into Your Mathom Closet

This is a quote from The Fellowship of the Ring by J.R.R. Tolkien:

So, though there was still some store of weapons in the Shire, these were used mostly as trophies, hanging above hearths or on walls, or gathered into the museum at Michel Delving. The Mathom-house it was called; for anything that Hobbits had no immediate use for, but were unwilling to throw away, they called a mathom. Their dwellings were apt to become rather crowded with mathoms, and many of the presents that passed from hand to hand were of that sort.

So mathom, strictly speaking, refers to that class of item that while useless, is too delightful to throw away. Most people have a closet somewhere in the house where at least a few pieces hide.

Here on Grex, mathom is also a program that allows you to create text gifts for the people you like. Larry Kestenbaum (polygon) suggested that we adopt the idea here on Grex, and Valerie Mates (valerie) created the program.

To run the Mathom program, type:

Ok: mathom

at any PicoSpan prompt. The program is pretty much self-explanatory. The commands may all be abbreviated to one letter. So for instance, when you see the prompt:

Look (at your mathom), Create (new mathom), Someone (else's mathom to look at), Who (has mathom?), Help, or Exit?

that means you can enter L to look at your mathom, C to create a new mathom, etc.

The first time someone gives you a mathom, the program will send you mail to let you know about it. Once you have mathom (either because you created it or because someone gave it to you), you can look at it or give it away.

Table of Contents

Finger

Recall that when you create a Grex account through the Newuser program, you are asked for some information about yourself. Your answers to those questions are stored in a file in your home directory called .plan.

You can see someone's .plan by using the finger command. At a PicoSpan prompt, type:

Ok: finger mta

to see mta's .plan. (You'll also see information about when mta last logged on, and a few other things.) If you enter finger with no parameters:

Ok: finger

you'll get a list of everyone who's on Grex right now.

Note that finger is a standard Internet protocol, so if you want them to, everyone on the Net can see what's in your .plan; or you can set it so that it is completely private. You can switch back and forth between these settings using the change program.

Table of Contents

Going One-on-One: Using Chat, Write, Talk, and Tel

Chat, Write, Talk, and Tel are all programs that let you converse with another user one-on-one in real time. This can be a good way to make arrangements on-line to meet with friends for dinner later, or to get to know another user more personally, even though you live thousands of miles apart.

Chat and Write

Chat and Write are essentially the same program with different options. Both allow one user on Grex to type text which then appears on another user's terminal, and vice-versa. Chat passes characters as they arrive, one character at a time, and Write passes them one line at a time.

To use Chat to talk to user aruba, type:

Ok: chat aruba

From now on, everything you type will appear on aruba's screen. This could potentially be quite confusing and annoying to the recipient, so there are a few rules of ettiquette which have been established to make Chat and Write work more smoothly:

The person initiating the call waits for the other person to respond before saying anything.
To signal that it's the other persons turn to type, end your transmission with an o (for over) on its own line.
Wait for the other person to signal with an o that it's your turn to type.
When you want to end the conversation, type oo? (for over and out) on a line by itself. The other person will respond with oo if he or she is ready to sign off.

To exit Chat or Write, type Ctrl-D.

When someone taps you to talk using Chat or Write, youll see a line on your screen that looks like:

message from popcorn on ttyq8 at 20:47...

Respond with:

Ok: write

or

Ok: chat

Talk

Talk is the most sophisticated of the conversational programs. It draws a horizontal line halfway down your screen. Whatever you type appears on the top half of the screen, and whatever the other person types appears on the bottom. That keeps the text from getting tangled.

You must have your terminal type set correctly for Talk to work. If you get all the text as a single column down the left side of your screen, it means your terminal type is set up incorrectly.

When someone taps you to talk using the Talk program, you'll see something like:

Message from Talk_Daemon@grex.org at 13:23 ...
talk: connection requested by aruba@grex.org.
talk: respond with: talk aruba@grex.org

Actually all you need to type to respond is:

Ok: talk aruba

The reason that the Talk program gave you a full Internet address is that Talk (unlike Chat and Write) is capable of connecting you to people on other machines besides Grex.

To exit talk press your interrupt character (usually Ctrl-C).

Tel

Tel is short for telegram, and it's a program you can use to send a quick message to someone else on Grex. To send a message to aruba, type:

Ok: !tel aruba

Then enter your text:

Telegram to aruba on ttyrf...
Msg: How's it going?

The message you typed will then appear on aruba's screen.

Preventing People from Writing to You

If you don't want anyone to tap you for a one-to-one conversation right now, you can close the chat door by going to any PicoSpan prompt and typing:

Ok: mesg n

That will tell people who try to chat with you using Chat, Write, Talk, or Tel that you're busy right now and not accepting messages. If you decide that you're open to conversation later in your session, you can re-open the chat door by typing:

Ok: mesg y

It's possible to be more selective about who is allowed to chat you and who isn't. The change program allows you to set those options.

Table of Contents

Text Files and Editors

Your Home Directory

When someone creates a new account on Grex, a place is set aside for that account's files. This is called the account's home directory. Certain programs store information in files there, and on top of that you can put any files you want in your home directory, though we ask that you keep your total disk usage to under 1 megabyte.

Most files on UNIX systems are text files, meaning they contain only printable characters (letters, numbers, and punctuation) and a few formatting characters (end-of-line markers and tabs) but no fancy formatting stuff. Occasionally you may want to create or modify text files in your home directory - such as the .plan file mentioned in the section on Finger.

Editors

An editor program allows you to change text files and create new ones. Its also useful if you enter a long response in the Mail program or in PicoSpan, and then realize you made a mistake on the first line and need to go back and change it.

Most editors show you the full text of a file and allow you to move around in your text and to cut and paste blocks of text in different places. An editor is like a word processor, but without a lot of formatting commands (like boldface and italics) which don't apply to text files. Grex offers a number of different editors. Which one you should use should depend on what you're used to and how much fancy stuff you want to do.

Nano

Nano is probably the best bet for a novice Grex user. It's designed to fit well with the Pine mailer (it was written by the same people), so if you selected Pine, you'll want to use Nano for a consistent interface. To use Nano to edit a file called foo, type:

Ok: nano foo

Nano shows you a list of commands you can type at the bottom of the screen, which makes it easy to get started without learning a lot of keystrokes first. The only drawbacks to using it are that it's a bit slow and you can't do anything fancy with it. But it's usually fast enough, and you usually don't need to do anything fancy.

Joe

Joe is another simple editor you may want to try - it is similar to Wordstar. Type:

Ok: joe foo

to edit the file foo with Joe. You can get it to show you a list of commands right on the screen by typing Ctrl-K followed by h.

vi, emacs, and the rest

If you are an experienced UNIX user, you can choose one of the standard UNIX editors. These are not for the timid, though.

Using an Editor from within PicoSpan or Mail

In order to use an editor from within PicoSpan or Mail or another program, you must first tell the system what editor you prefer. Type:

Ok: !change

and follow the prompts to do that. Then if you're typing a response in PicoSpan and would like to edit it in your editor, enter a colon on a line by itself:

>:

and PicoSpan will put you in your editor. To do the same thing in Mail, type:

& ~v

Table of Contents

Uploading and Downloading Files

There are times when you may want to copy a file that is currently on Grex onto your home computer, or vice-versa. Knowing how to do that is a very useful skill, because it allows you to compose long messages offline, to save text you like on your home computer (so you need not log onto Grex to get to it), and even to exchange personal computer programs with other users.

Copying a file from Grex to your home computer is called downloading the file. (Think of Grex as being upstairs, and your PC as being downstairs.) Sending files the other way is called uploading.

Transferring Files over a Dial-up Connection

There are several protocols used for transferring files over a dial-up connection.

The ones Grex supports are Kermit, X-Modem, Y-Modem, and Z-Modem. Which protocol you use depends on what your communications software will support. Check your documentation for references to transferring files.

Downloading over a Dial-up Connection

Downloading a file is a two-step process. First decide what protocol you are using, and be sure you know the filename. We'll suppose the file is called waffles.

1. First tell Grex to send the file. How you do this depends on the protocol you're using:

Kermit: | Ok: !kermit -s waffles
X-Modem: | Ok: !sx waffles
Y-Modem: | Ok: !sy waffles
Z-Modem: | Ok: !sz waffles

2. As soon as you get a message that says the file is ready to be sent, tell your communications program to receive the file. How you do that depends on what program youre using; you'll have to read the documentation to find out.

Uploading over a Dial-up Connection

Uploading is also a two-step process. Decide what protocol you're using, then:

1. First tell Grex to receive the file. Depending on the protocol, you would type:

Kermit: | Ok: !kermit -r
X-Modem: | Ok: !rx
Y-Modem: | Ok: !ry
Z-Modem: | Ok: !rz

2. After you get a message that says Grex is ready to receive, go to your communications program and tell it to send the file. Again, how you do that depends on your program, so check the documentation.

FTP

If you connect to Grex over the Internet using telnet, the best way to transfer files to your home computer is by using FTP. FTP stands for File Transfer Protocol, and you'll need an FTP program on your home computer to transfer files. How it works will depend on just which program you have, but basically you want to tell it to open a connection to grex.org, then give it your login ID and password.

After you're connected, if you have a graphical interface you should be able to drag and drop the files you want to move. If you have a command-line interface (such as the one that comes with Windows 95), the commands are get to get a file from Grex and put to put a file onto Grex.

Table of Contents

UNIX (Whats That?)

Grex runs a version of the UNIX operating system called SunOS 4.1.4. SunOS is the underlying software system that lets all the programs you use (such as PicoSpan, Mail, etc.) run, much as DOS, Mac OS, and Windows 95 allow programs to run on home computers. There are many versions of UNIX in existence; ours originally came from Sun Microsystems Inc., the makers of the Sun-4 computer Grex runs on now.

Explaining the intricacies of UNIX is a formidable task, well beyond the scope of this handbook. But you are welcome to use Grex to learn as much as you can about it, studying the documentation online and asking lots of questions.

Table of Contents

Bibliography

Much of what you need to know to make full use of all GREX's facilities can be found in a good UNIX reference. The most of the rest can be found in a good Internet reference. We recommend you check out the local library! Here are a few places to start:

Take me To Your Modem: a pocket guide to GREX
Cyberspace Communications, 1993

UNIX for Dummies by John R. Levine
IDG Books Worldwide 1993

Internet for Dummies by John R. Levine
IDG Books Worldwide 1993

Zen and the Art of the Internet: A Beginner's Guide by Brendon P. Kehoe
Prentice Hall, 1993

The Virtual Community: Homesteading on the Electronic Frontier by Howard Rheingold
Addison-Wesley, 1993

Table of Contents

The GREX Statement of Principles

This system is intended to foster community education and the spiritual and intellectual enrichment of its users, through the peaceable interchange of ideas.

The members of this system hope to attract a large, diverse, and mature group of thinking individuals and thereby to contribute to a better-informed citizenry.

Governance of the system is based on cooperative principles, including open membership, democratic control, and nonprofit economics.

This is an open-access system; the public is welcome. However, we encourage regular users to become members and help support the system financially. Voting on system policy matters is restricted to members.

It should go without saying that the system is specifically NOT intended for any illegal purpose.

Users are asked to be considerate of others, and are especially asked to make a point of setting a good example for those few who may from time to time fail to return the favor.

INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE                      DEPARTMENT OF THE TREASURY
DISTRICT DIRECTOR
P.O. BOX 2508
CINCINATI, OH 45201
                                        Employer Identification Number:
Date:                                       38-2998091
        JUL 13 1998                     DLN:
                                            17053155035048
                                        Contact Person:
CYBERSPACE COMMUNICATIONS                   D. A. DOWNING
C/O JAN WOLTER                          Contact Telephone Number:
406 WEST LIBERTY                            (513) 241-5199
ANN ARBOR, MI 48103-4343                Accounting Period Ending
                                            DECEMBER 31
                                        Form 990 Required:
                                            YES
                                        Addendum Applies:
                                            NO

Dear Applicant:

   Based on information supplied, and assuming your operations will be as
stated in your application for recognition of exemption, we have determined
you are exempt from federal income tax under sections 501(a) of the Internal
Revenue Code as an organization described in section 501(c)(3).

   We have further determined that you are not a private foundation within
the meaning of section 509(a) of the Code, because you are an organization
described in sections 509(a)(1) and 170(b)(1)(A)(vi).

   If your sources of support, or your purposes, character, or method of
operation change, please let us know so we can consider the effect of
the change on your exempt status and foundation status.  In the case of
an amendment to your organizational document or bylaws, please send
us a copy of the amended document or bylaws.  Also, you should inform
us of all changes in your name or address.

   As of January 1, 1984, you are liable for taxes under the Federal
Insurance Contributions Act (social security taxes) on remuneration of
$100 or more you pay to each of your employees during a calender year.
You are not liable for the tax imposed under the Federal Unemployment Act
(FUTA).

   Since you are not a private foundation, you are not subject to
the excise taxes under Chapter 42 of the Code.  However, if you are
involved in an excess benefit transaction, that transaction might be
subject to the excise taxes of section 4958.  Additionally, you are
not automatically exempt from other federal excise taxes.  If you have
any questions about excise, employment, or other federal taxes, please
contact your key district office.

   Grantors and contributors may rely on this determination unless the
Internal Revenue Service publishes a notice to the contrary.  However,
if you lose your section 509(a)(1) status, a grantor or contributor
may not rely on this dtermination if he or she was in part responsible
for, or was aware of, the act or failure to act, or the substantial or
material change on the part of the organization that resulted in your
loss of such status, or if he or she acquired knowledge that the Internal
Revenue Service had given notice that you would no longer be classified
as a section 509(a)(1) organization.

   Donors may deduct contributions to you as provided in section 170
of the Code.  Bequests, legacies, devises, transfers, or gifts to you
or for your use are deductable for federal estate and gift tax purposes
if they meet the applicable provisions of Code sections 2055, 2106 and
2522.

   Contribution deductions are allowable to donors only the the extent
that their contributions are gifts, with no consideration received.
Ticket purchases and similar payments in conjunction with fundraising
events may not necessarily qualify as deductable contributions, depending
on the circumstances.  See Revenue Ruling 67-246, published in Cumulative
Bulletin 1967-2, on page 104, which sets forth guidelines regarding
the deductibility, as charitable contributions, of payments made
by taxpayers for admission to or other participation in fundraising
activities for charity.

   In the head of this letter we have indicated whether you must file Form
990, Return of Organization Exempt From Income Tax.  If Yes is indicated,
you are required to file Form 990 only if your gross receipts each year
are normally more than $25,000.  However, if you receive a Form 990
package in the mail, please file the return even if you do not exceed
the gross receipts test.  If you are required to file, simply attach
the label provided, check the box in the heading to indicate that your
annual gross receipts are normally $25,000 or less, and sign the return.

   If a return is required, it must be filed by the 15th day of the fifth
month after the end of your annual accounting period.  A penalty of
$20 a day is charged when a return is filed late, unless there is a
reasonable cause for the delay.  However, the maximum penalty charged
cannot exceed $10,000 or 5 percent of your gross receipts for the year,
whichever is less.  For organizations with gross receipts exceeding
$1,000,000 in any year, the penalty is $100 per day per return, unless
there is a reasonable cause for the delay.  The maximum penalty for an
organization with gross receipts exceeding $1,000,000 shall not exceed
$50,000.  This penalty may also be charged if a return is not complete,
so be sure your return is complete when you file it.

   You are required to make your annual return available for public
inspection for three days after the return is due.  You are also required
to make available a copy of your exemption application, any supporting
documents, and this exemption letter.  Failure to make these documents
available for public inspection may subject you to a penalty of $20
per day for each day there is a failure to comply (up to a maximum of
$10,000 in the case of an annual return).

   You are not required to file federal income tax returns unless you are
subject to the tax on unrelated business income under sections 511 of
the Code.  If you are subject to this tax, you must file an income tax
return on Form 990-T, Exempt Organization Business Income Tax Return.
In this letter we are not determining whether any of your present or
proposed activities are unrelated trade or business as defined in
section 513 of the Code.

   You need an employer identification number even if you have no
employees.  If an employer identification number was not entered on your
application, a number will be assigned to you and you will be advised of
it.  Please use that number on all returns you file and in all
correspondence with the Internal Revenue Service.

   This determination is based on evidence that your funds are dedicated
to the purposes listed in section 501(c)3 of the Code.  To assure your
continued exemption, you shoud keep records to show that funds are
expended only for those purposes.  If you distribute funds to other
organizations, your records should show whether they are exempt under
section 501(c)(3).  In cases where the recipient organization is not
exempt under section 501(c)(3), there should be evidence that the funds
will remain dedicated to the required purposes and that they will be
used for those purposes by the recipient.

   If distributions are made to individuals, case histories regarding the
recipients should be kept showing names, addresses, purposes of awards,
manner of selection, relationship (if any) to members, officers,
trustees or donors of funds to you, so that any and all distributions
made to individuals can be substantiated upon request by the Internal
Revenue Service.  (Revenue Ruling 56-304, C.B. 1956-2, page 306.)

   If we have indicated in the heading of this letter that an addendum
applies, the enclosed addendum is an integral part of this letter.

   Because this letter could help you resolve any questions about
your exempt status and foundation status, you should keep it in your
permanent records.

   If you have any questions, please contact the person whose name and
telephone number are shown in the heading of this letter.

                                 Sincerely yours,

                                        <Glen E. Henderson>

                                  District Director

                                                Letter 947 (DO/CG)

$Id: irs.xhtml 1438 2014-03-23 16:39:04Z kentn $

Cyberspace Communications Policy Log

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

The basic rules for the operation of Cyberspace Communications are laid out by the bylaws. However, over the years, various other policies have been set.

Membership Referenda

Any Cyberspace Communications member can propose a referendum for vote by the membership. The results of such votes are binding on the board and can only be overturned by another member referendum. Bylaw Amendments are not listed here (see the bylaws), nor are unsuccessful motions. All motions, can be found at the member vote page.

Restriction of Outgoing Net Access - Passed April 6, 1994 Cyberspace Communications (Grex) will restrict outgoing Internet access such that only those who are verified and paying membership dues will receive this service.

NOTE: This motion is modified by the next one.

Restriction of Outgoing Net Access - Passed August 17, 1994

The following internet services enrich the Grex community, do not use much bandwidth, and do not provide much potential for internet mischief; therefore they should be made available to all:
Finger
Whois
Ping
Mail (incoming and outgoing)
Incoming Usenet News
Incoming Telnet
Incoming FTP
Incoming Lynx
Talk (and its various permutations)
Archie
Veronica
WAIS
Gopher (with all Telnet capabilities disabled)

The following services will be restricted to VERIFIED GREX MEMBERS and VERIFIED GREX USERS (however the board shall define that term) because of the potential for world-wide mischief:
Outgoing Usenet News

The following services will be restricted to VERIFIED GREX MEMBERS in good standing, because these services utilize a lot of bandwidth, offer less of a benefit to the Grex community as a whole, and/or hold the potential for system cracking and other undesirable activities:
Outgoing FTP
Outgoing Telnet
Outgoing Lynx
Gopher (with telnet capability enabled.)
IRC

Being that the major objection to open access for the above services is the lack of available bandwidth on Grex's internet link, It is understood that any of these services may be made available to all VERIFIED USERS as well as VERIFIED MEMBERS as soon as Grex acquires a link of suitable power and robustness.

In order to maintain the integrity of both Grex, and of the Internet as a whole, the Grex board shall have the power to restrict or deny internet access to groups or individuals who pose a security risk, or who engage in inappropriate behavior (as defined by the Grex board).

The board may also make modifications to this proposal without resorting to a member vote in the case of an emergency situation, or if some provision of this proposal proves to be technically impossible to implement.

Blue Ribbon Campaign - Passed December 17, 1998
That Grex place an endorsement of the Blue Ribbon Campaign for Online Freedom of Expression on its web page. This endorsement should stay in place at least until the fate of the recently-enacted Federal statute which prohibits the display of material 'harmful to minors' in certain circumstances is decided by the Federal courts, but may be left up longer at the discretion of Grex's webmasters.
Michigan Public Act 33 Lawsuit - Passed June 21, 1999
To support continued participation of Cyberspace Communications, Inc., as a plaintiff in the lawsuit aimed at overturning Michigan Public Act 33 of 1999. A vote of "YES" shall be construed as supporting continued participation, while a vote of "NO" shall be construed as supporting withdrawal from the lawsuit.

Board Motions

The Cyberspace Communications board sometimes makes motions authorizing certain actions or establishing certain procedures. These could be overridden by another board vote or a member referendum. This page lists only motions of lasting interests. It does not include motions to experiment with connecting to the internet for three months, nor motions to purchase a rubber stamp, which are of mere historical interest. More complete board minutes are also available on-line.

Disk Quotas - April 19, 1994
Staff is authorized to implement disk quotas for the efficient management of disk space. Staff may allow increases in quotas of individual users for special needs. Space will be allocated without consideration of membership status. Users may appeal the decisions of staff to the Board.

NOTE: Staff has never yet done this, but remains authorized to do so.

Staff Membership - November 16, 1994
Staff with permanent root access may at its discretion grant specific resources to qualified individuals for the purpose of performing work that is beneficial to Grex. Examples of such resources would be write access to selected directories in order to modify data files or to install software. In the event of an emergency, temporary root access may be granted by any permanent root.

Permanent root access, access to the staff conference, and access to the "baff" mailing list shall be with the advice and consent of the Board.

Grex Ohio - August 23, 1995
The organization "GrexOhio" is permitted to use the name "Grex" in their name "GrexOhio", pending the adoption by the Cyberspace Communications, Inc/ board of an associated club charter policy, to which GrexOhio will be required to adhere.

NOTE: GrexOhio has pretty much evaporated but this sets a precedent.

Verification Policy - September 27, 1995
(1) Anyone requesting access to Grex services for which verification is required shall present proof of his or her identity. Members and non-members will be held to the same verification criteria. In order to be considered verified, a person shall submit a photocopy of an item of acceptable identification and a signed letter requesting the access.

(2) The acceptable items of identification are government-issued ID, school-issued ID, library-issued ID, or a personal check written to Cyberspace Communications Inc. by the person requesting access. To be accepted, the item must be currently valid (i.e. not expired), must identify the person by name, and must include additional identifying information other than a photograph (such as home address, passport number, or name of school).

(3) There shall be one individual, referred to hereafter as "verifier", who is responsible for accepting verification requests and ID, notifying the appropriate staff member(s) so that access may be granted if the criteria of (1) and (2) are met, and notifying the requester if the ID is not acceptable.

(4) The board shall solicit volunteers and appoint the verifier. The term of office is one year and is renewable. Any verified user is eligible for the post of verifier. If a volunteer for the post is not currently verified, then for the purpose of gaining eligibility he or she may present identification to the board that meets the criteria enumerated in (2).

(5) In the case of personal checks submitted to the treasurer of Cyberspace Communications Inc., the treasurer may also verify a user, provided the check meets the criteria of (2) and is accompanied by a signed letter as required in (1).

(6) An individual whose request for verification is denied may appeal the decision to the board. The board's ruling on appeals is final.

Computer Room Keys - August 23, 1995
Authorize root access for Dave Lovelace (davel), Rob Henderson (robh), and Scott Helmke (scott), and to authorize keys for all root staff.

NOTE: This motion says that any root staff who need and want keys to the machine room may have them.

Deceased Users - November 15, 1995
Staff will honor requests to permanently reserve an account of a user who has died.
Message Filters - June 26, 1996
Moved that the board express no objection to the installation of software that allows a user to filter or permit other specific users to send them real-time messages.

NOTE: This is about .yeswrite and .nowrite files, which allow a person to filter which users may 'write' or 'talk' to them. They were briefly controversial.

Delinquent Board Members - June 28, 1999
If a board member is late paying his or her dues, the treasurer will inform the entire board by e-mail. If he or she still has not paid by the time the "New Business" item is reached at the end of the next board meeting, the board will consider the matter and take appropriate action. This may include declaring the board member's seat vacant.
Institutional Membership Requirements - March 21, 2001
In addition to those applicable requirements for individual memberships, the requirements for institutional Grex memberships shall be:
1) A designated contact person who shall be responsible for all use of the member account.
2) Verifiable personal identification for the designated contact person (subject to the same ID requirements as individual memberships)
3) Renewal of institutional memberships requires an update of the contact ID.

Last Update Sat Jul 14 01:10:32 EDT 2001

$Id: policy.xhtml 1534 2015-11-10 05:36:54Z kentn $